Good morning!
صباح الخير
Are you awake?
هل أنتم يقظون؟
They took my name tag, but I wanted to ask you,
أخذوا مني البطاقة، ولكن كنت أريد أن أسألكم،
did anyone here write their name on the tag in Arabic?
هل كتب أحدكم اسمه بالعربية على البطاقة؟
Anyone! No one? All right, no problem.
واحد! لا أحد. حسنا، لا مشكلة.
Once upon a time, not long ago,
كان يا ما كان، ليس بقديم الزمان،
I was sitting in a restaurant with my friend, ordering food.
أنا وصديقتي جالستان بمطعم نطلب الطعام.
So I looked at the waiter and said,
فنظرت إلى الشخص الذي يساعدنا وقلت له:
"Do you have a menu (Arabic)?"
"هل لديك لائحة الطعام؟"
He looked at me strangely, thinking that he misheard.
فنظر إلي مستغربا، ظانّا بأنه لم يسمعني بشكل جيد
He said, "Sorry? (English)."
فقال لي: عذرًا (بالإنجليزية)؟
I said, "The menu (Arabic), please."
قلت له: لائحة الطعام، لو سمحت!
He replied, "Don't you know what they call it?"
قال لي: ألا تعرفين ماذا يسمونها؟
"I do."
بلى!
He said, "No! It's called "menu" (English), or "menu" (French)."
قال: لا! تسمى Menu (بالإنجليزية) أو Menu (بالفرنسية)،
Is the French pronunciation correct?
هل اللفظ صحيح بالفرنسية؟
"Come, come, take care of this one!" said the waiter.
تعالِ، تعالِ، وتولى أمر هذه!
He was disgusted when talking to me, as if he was saying to himself,
اشمئز وكأنه أثناء محاولته للحديث معي يقول في نفسه
"If this was the last girl on Earth, I wouldn't look at her!"
لو كنتِ آخر فتاة في العالم، لن أنظر إليها!
What's the meaning of saying "menu" in Arabic?
ما معنى أن تقول لائحة الطعام؟!
Two words made a Lebanese young man judge a girl as being backward
كلمتان جعلتا شابا لبنانيا يحكم على فتاة جالسة لديه بالتخلف،
and ignorant.
بالجهل
How could she speak that way?
كيف تستطيع التحدث بهذه الطريقة؟
At that moment, I started thinking.
فأنا في تلك اللحظة بدأت أفكر
It made me mad.
تضايقت
It definitely hurts!
انجرحت، بكل تأكيد!
I'm denied the right to speak my own language in my own country?
أنا في بلدي و يمنع علي التحدث بلغتي؟!
Where could this happen?
أين يمكن حدوث هذا؟
How did we get here?
كيف وصلنا إلى هذه المرحلة؟
Well, while we are here, there are many people like me,
حسنًا، ونحن هنا، هنالك الكثير من أمثالي
who would reach a stage in their lives, where they involuntarily give up
يمكن أن يصلوا إلى مرحلة في حياتهم يتخلون فيها رغما عنهم
everything that has happened to them in the past,
عن كل شيء حصل في حياتهم في السابق
just so they can say that they're modern
لمجرّد أن يقولوا بأنهم معاصرون
and civilized.
و أنهم متحضرون
Should I forget all my culture, thoughts,
هل أنسى كل ثقافتي وكل أفكاري،
intellect and all my memories?
وكل مخزوني الفكري وكل ذكرياتي؟
Childhood stories might be the best memories we have of the war!
قد تكون أحلى ذكريات من الحرب هي قصص الطفولة!
Should I forget everything I learned in Arabic, just to conform?
هل أنسى كل ما تعلمته بالعربية لمجرد أن أندمج؟
To be one of them?
حتى أصبح أنا فردا منهم؟
Where's the logic in that?
أين المنطق في ذلك؟
Despite all that, I tried to understand him.
مع كل ذلك، حاولت أن أتفهمه
I didn't want to judge him with the same cruelty that he judged me.
ولا أريد أن أحكم عليه بنفس القسوة التي حكم علي بها
The Arabic language doesn't satisfy today's needs.
اللغة العربية لا تلبي احتياجات اليوم.
It's not a language for science,
ليست لغة إنتاج علمي
research,
ولا بحث
a language we're used to in universities,
ولا لغة نعتادها في الجامعة
a language we use in the workplace,
ولا لغة نتحدثها في العمل
a language we rely on if we were to perform an advanced research project,
وليست لغة نعتمدها في حال أردنا
and it definitely isn't a language we use at the airport.
و بالتأكيد ليست اللغة التي نستخدمها في المطار
If we did so, they'd strip us of our clothes.
فإن تكلمنا بالعربية سينزعون عنا جميع ملابسنا.
Where can I use it, then? We could all ask this question!
حسناً، أين يمكن أن نستخدمها؟ نستطيع جميعنا أن نسأل هذا السؤال!
So, you want us to use Arabic. Where are we to do so?
حسنًا، تريدين منا استخدام اللغة العربية، فأين لنا أن نستخدمها؟
This is one reality.
هذا واقع موجود
But we have another more important reality that we ought to think about.
ولكن يوجد لدينا واقع آخر أهم نريد أن نفكر به وننتبه له
Arabic is the mother tongue.
اللغة العربية أو اللغة الأم
Research says that mastery of other languages
تقول الأبحاث والتقارير بأن إتقان اللغات الأخرى يتطلب إتقان اللغة الأم
Mastery of the mother tongue is a prerequisite for creative expression in other languages.
أما الإبداع باللغات الأخرى فله شرط أساسي وهو إتقان اللغة الأم
How?
كيف؟
Gibran Khalil Gibran,
جبران خليل جبران
when he first started writing, he used Arabic.
عندما بدأ في الكتابة، كان يكتب بالعربية.
All his ideas, imagination and philosophy
كل أفكاره وخياله وباطنه والماوراء والفلسفة
were inspired by this little boy in the village
استلهمها من هذا الطفل الجالس في القرية
where he grew up, smelling a specific smell,
التي تربى فيها على رائحة معينة
hearing a specific voice,
على صوت معين
and thinking a specific thought.
على فكرة معينة
So, when he started writing in English, he had enough baggage.
فعندما بدأ في الكتابة بالإنجليزية، كان لديه مخزون فكري كبير.
Even when he wrote in English,
حتى عندما كان يكتب بالإنجليزية
when you read his writings in English, you smell the same smell,
عندما نقرأ كتاباته بالإنجليزية، نشم نفس الرائحة!
sense the same feeling.
نحس بنفس الإحساس
You can imagine that that's him writing in English,
نستطيع أن نتخيل أنه هو نفسه الذي يبدع بالإنجليزية،
the same boy who came from the mountain. From a village on Mount Lebanon.
هو ذاته الذي أتى من الجبل. من قرية في جبل لبنان
So, this is an example no one can argue with.
فهذا مثال لا يستطيع أحد القول بأنه غير صحيح.
Second, it's often said that if you want to kill a nation,
ثانيًا، يقال بأنه إذا أردت قتل شعب،
the only way to kill a nation,
الطريقة الوحيدة لقتل شعب،
is to kill its language.
هي بأن تقتل لغته.
This is a reality that developed societies are aware of.
وهذا الواقع تعرفه الشعوب المتطورة.
The Germans, French, Japanese and Chinese, all these nations are aware of this.
الألمان والفرنسيون واليابانيون والصينيون، جميع الشعوب تعرف هذه الحقيقة.
That's why they legislate to protect their language.
فلذلك تسن القوانين لحماية لغتها.
They make it sacred.
ولذلك تقدس تلك اللغة.
That's why they use it in production, they pay a lot of money to develop it.
ولذلك تنتج بها، وتدفع مبالغ ضخمة لتطويرها.
Do we know better than them?
فهل نعرف نحن أكثر منهم؟
All right,
حسنا
we aren't from the developed world,
إذا لم نكن نحن من دول العالم الأول،
this advanced thinking hasn't reached us yet,
و لم يصل إلينا هذا الفكر المتطور بعد
and we would like to catch up with the civilized world.
و نريد اللحاق بهذا العالم المتحضر
Countries that were once like us, but decided to strive for development,
الدول التي كانت مثلنا، وقررت أن تسعى وراء التنمية
do research,
وأن تنتج أبحاثا
and catch up with those countries,
وتلحق بتلك الدول
such as Turkey, Malaysia and others,
مثل تركيا وماليزيا وغيرهم،
they carried their language with them as they were climbing the ladder,
هؤلاء حملوا لغتهم وهم يصعدون هذا السلم،
protected it like a diamond.
مثل الألماسة. حافظوا عليها.
They kept it close to them.
جعلوها قريبة منهم.
Because if you get any product from Turkey or elsewhere
لأنه إذا وصلكم أي إنتاج من تركيا أو غيرها
and it's not labeled in Turkish,
ليس مكتوبًا عليه باللغة التركية
then it isn't a local product.
فإنه ليس إنتاجًا محليًّا.
You wouldn't believe it's a local product.
لن تصدقوا بأنه إنتاج محلي.
They'd go back to being consumers,
وسيعودون إلى كونهم مستهلكين.
clueless consumers, like we are most of the time.
ومستهلكين بغباء، كما نفعل نحن معظم الوقت.
So, in order for them to innovate and produce, they had to protect their language.
فليبدعوا ولينتجوا كان من الضروري أن يحافظوا على لغتهم.
If I say, "Freedom, sovereignty, independence (Arabic),"
إذا قلت "حرية، سيادة، استقلال"، بما يذكركم هذا؟
Regardless of the who, how and why.
بغض النظر مع من وكيف ولماذا..
Language isn't just for conversing, just words coming out of our mouths.
اللغة ليست فقط للأحاديث، وأي كلمات تخرج من الفم. أبدا.
Language represents specific stages in our lives,
اللغة تمثل مراحل معينة في حياتنا.
and terminology that is linked to our emotions.
ترتبط عاطفتنا بها، وترتبط بتلك المصطلحات.
So when we say, "Freedom, sovereignty, independence,"
لذلك عندما نقول حرية، سيادة، استقلال،
each one of you draws a specific image in their own mind,
كل فرد منكم يرسم صورة في ذهنه
there are specific feelings
هنالك كلمات معينة، أحاسيس معينة،
of a specific day in a specific historical period.
ليوم معين، لفترة تاريخية معينة.
Language isn't one, two or three words or letters put together.
فاللغة ليست كلمة وحرف وحرفان وثلاثة مصفوفة.
It's an idea inside that relates to how we think,
هي فكرة في الداخل ترتبط بكيف نفكر ونرى الآخر وكيف يرانا هو.
What is our intellect?
ما هو مخزوننا الفكري
How do you say whether this guy understands or not?
لماذا نقول هذا الشخص يفهم وهذا لا يفهم؟
So, if I say, "Freedom, sovereignty, independence (English),"
فإذا قلت لكم "حرية، سيادة، استقلال" (بالانجليزية)
or if your son came up to you and said,
أو إذا أتى إليكم إبنكم وقال لكم:
"Dad, have you lived through the period of the freedom (English) slogan?"
داد، هل عايشتم ذاك التاريخ الذي تخلله شعارالحرية (بالإنجليزية) وما إلى ذلك؟
How would you feel?
فبم ستشعرون؟
If you don't see a problem,
إن لم تشعروا بمشكلة
then I'd better leave, and stop talking in vain.
فأجدى بي أن أغادر على أن أتكلم بلا جدوى
The idea is that these expressions remind us of a specific thing.
الفكرة هي بأن هذه التعابير تذكرنا بشيء معين
I have a francophone friend who's married to a French man.
لدي صديقة فرانكفونية متزوجة من شخص فرنسي
I asked her once how things were going.
كنت أسألها يوما عن أحوالها وما إلى ذلك
She said, "Everything is fine,
فقالت لي "كل شيء بأفضل حال"
but once, I spent a whole night asking and trying to translate
"ولكن مرّت ليلة قضيتها كاملة أسأله وأحاول أن أترجم له"
the meaning of the word 'toqborni' for him."
معنى كلمة "تقبرني"
(Laughter)
(ضحك) (تصفيق)
The poor woman had mistakenly told him "toqborni,"
المسكينة قالت له "تقبرني" هفوا.
and then spent the whole night trying to explain it to him.
فقضت الليل بطوله تشرح له
Does she want to commit suicide?
أم أنها تريد أن تنتحر؟
'Bury me?' (English)"
ادفني (بالإنجليزية) مثلا
This is one of the few examples.
فهذا من أصغر الأمثلة
It made us feel that she's unable to tell that word to her husband,
و مع ذلك يجعلنا نشعر بأنها غير قادرة على قول هذه الكلمة لزوجها لأنه لن يفهمها
She said to me, "He listens to Fairuz with me,
و قالت لي: "يستمع معي إلى أغاني فيروز
and one night, I tried to translate for him
لكن في ليلة من الليالي، حاولت أن أترجم له
so he can feel what I feel when I listen to Fairuz."
لكي يشعر بما أشعر به عندما أسمتع إلى فيروز
The poor woman tried to translate this for him:
فالمسكينة حاولت أن تترجم له:
"From them I extended my hands and stole you --"
منهم مددت يدي وسرقتك
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And here's the pickle:
وهنا تكمن العقدة: "ولأنك لهم، أعدت يداي وتركتك."
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Translate that for me.
ترجموها لنا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, what have we done to protect the Arabic language?
حسنا، ماذا فعلناه لنحمي اللغة العربية؟
We turned this into a concern of the civil society,
حولنا هذا الموضوع إلى قضية مجتمع مدني
and we launched a campaign to preserve the Arabic language.
وأطلقنا حملة الحفاظ على اللغة العربية
Even though many people told me, "Why do you bother?
مع أن الكثير من الناس قالوا لي: ما لك وهذا؟
Forget about this headache and go have fun."
تسلي وامرحي ودعي عنك أوجاع الرأس.
No problem!
لا مشكلة!
The campaign to preserve Arabic launched a slogan that says,
حملة الحفاظ على اللغة العربية أطلقت شعار يقول:
"I talk to you from the East, but you reply from the West."
أخاطبك من الشرق، فترد من الغرب.
We didn't say, "No! We do not accept this or that."
لم نقل: لا! ولن نقبل! ونحن هذه اللغة ونحن نعمل...
We didn't adopt this style because that way, we wouldn't be understood.
لم نتبع هذا الأسلوب لأننا لن نفهم بهذه الطريقة
And when someone talks to me that way, I hate the Arabic language.
وعندما يحدثني أحد بهذه الطريقة، أكره اللغة العربية.
We say--
نحن نقول
(Applause)
-(تصفيق)-
We want to change our reality,
نحن نريد أن نرى واقع ظروفنا
and be convinced in a way that reflects our dreams, aspirations and day-to-day life.
وأن نقتنع بطريقة تحاكي أحلامنا ويومياتنا وطموحاتنا
In a way that dresses like us and thinks like we do.
طريقة تلبس نفس ملابسنا، وتفكر بنفس الطريقة التي نفكر بها
So, "I talk to you from the East, but you reply from the West"
فـ"أخاطبك من الشرق، فترد من الغرب" وضعت أصبعها على الجرح
Something very easy, yet creative and persuasive.
شيء سهل جدًا، لكنه مبدع ومقنع.
After that, we launched another campaign
بعد ذلك، أطلقنا حملة أخرى
with scenes of letters on the ground.
فيها مشاهد الأحرف موضوعة على الأرض
You've seen an example of it outside,
رأيتم مثالًا عليها في الخارج
a scene of a letter surrounded by black and yellow tape
مشهد حرف وحوله شريط بالأصفر والأسود، كتب عليه: لا تقتل لغتك.
We really shouldn't kill our language.
حقّا، يجب علينا جميعًا ألا نقتل لغتنا.
If we were to kill the language, we'd have to find an identity.
لأن اللغة إن قتلناها سنضطر للبحث عن هوية.
We'd have to find an existence.
سنعود للبحث عن وجود.
We'd go back to the beginning.
سنعود للبدء من الصفر.
This is beyond just missing our chance of being modern and civilized.
وهذا يتخطى مجرد خسارتنا للقدرة على أن نكون متحضرين ومعاصرين
After that we released photos of guys and girls wearing the Arabic letter.
بعدها أصدرنا صورا لشباب وشابات وهم يغمرون الحرف العربي
Photos of "cool" guys and girls.
صور لشباب وشابات "كوول"
We are very cool!
نحن جدًّا "كوول"
And to whoever might say, "Ha! You used an English word!"
ومن سيقول لي: ها! إنك قد استخدمت كلمة انجليزية!
I say, "No! I adopt the word 'cool.'"
أقول له: لا! أنا أتبنى كلمة "كوول"
Let them object however they want, but give me a word that's nicer
دعوهم يعترضون كيفما شاؤوا، فليعطوني كلمة أجمل منها.
and matches the reality better.
ومتجانسة مع واقعنا أكثر منها.
I will keep on saying "Internet"
سأظل أقول "أنترنيت". لن أقول: أنا ذاهبة إلى الشبكة العنكبوتية.
Because it doesn't fit! We shouldn't kid ourselves.
لأنها لا تتناغم! فهل نضحك على أنفسنا؟
But to reach this point, we all have to be convinced
ولكن لنصل إلى هذه النقطة، يجب علينا جميعًا أن نكون مقتنعين.
that we shouldn't allow anyone who is bigger
لا يجب أن ندع من هو أكبر
or thinks they have any authority over us when it comes to language,
و من يظن أن لديه السلطة على اللغة
to control us or make us think and feel what they want.
أن يتحكم بنا ويجعلنا نحس ونفكر بما يريده.
Creativity is the idea.
فالفكرة هي الإبداع.
So, if we can't reach space or build a rocket and so on,
فإذا كنا لا نستطيع الوصول إلى الفضاء وصنع صاروخ وغير ذلك.
At this moment, every one of you is a creative project.
في هذه اللحظة، كل شخص منكم هنا هو مشروع إبداع.
Creativity in your mother tongue is the path.
الإبداع باللغة الأم هو الطريق.
Let's start from this moment.
دعونا نبدأ من الآن، من هذه اللحظة.
Let's write a novel or produce a short film.
فلنكتب رواية، ننتج فلم قصير.
A single novel could make us global again.
رواية واحدة تستطيع أن تعيدنا إلى العالمية.
It could bring the Arabic language back to being number one.
تستطيع أن تعيد اللغة العربية إلى المركز الأول.
So, it's not true that there's no solution; there is a solution!
إذًا ليس صحيحيا أن لا حل للمشكلة، بل الحل موجود!
But we have to know that, and be convinced that a solution exists,
لكن دعونا ننتبه ونقتنع بوجود حل.
that we have a duty to be part of that solution.
وبواجب أن نكون جزءً من هذا الحل.
In conclusion, what can you do today?
وفي الختام، ما الذي تستطيعون فعله اليوم؟
Now, tweets, who's tweeting?
الآن، التغريدات، من يقوم بالتغريد؟
Please, I beg of you, even though my time has finished,
أرجوكم! بالفعل أرجوكم، مع أن الوقت انتهى
either Arabic, English, French or Chinese.
إما بالعربية، أو بالإنجليزية، أو بالفرنسية، أو بالصينية.
But don't write Arabic with Latin characters mixed with numbers!
لكن لا تكتبوا "معقول" كـ ma32oul!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
It's a disaster! That's not a language.
لأنها كارثة! لأن هذه ليست بلغة.
You'd be entering a virtual world with a virtual language.
لأنكم هنا دخلتم عالما افتراضيا بلغة افتراضية
It's not easy to come back from such a place and rise.
يصعب علينا أن نرتقي إلى ما يفوق مستواها أبدًا.
That's the first thing we can do.
فهذا هو أول شيء نستطيع فعله.
Second, there are many other things that we can do.
ثانيًا، هنالك الكثير من الأشياء التي نستطيع فعلها.
We're not here today to convince each other.
اليوم نحن لسنا هنا لإقناع بعضنا البعض.
We're here to bring attention to the necessity of preserving this language.
نحن هنا لننتبه إلى ضرورة المحافظة على هذه اللغة.
Now I will tell you a secret.
والآن سأخبركم بسر.
A baby first identifies its father
عندما يولد الطفل، أول طريقة يتعرف بها على والده هي عن طريق اللغة.
When my daughter is born, I'll tell her, "This is your father, honey (Arabic)."
فعندما تولد ابنتي، سأقول لها: هذا هو والدك يا حياتي.
I wouldn't say, "This is your dad, honey (English)."
لن أقول لها: هذا هو والدك، عزيزتي (بالإنجليزية).
And in the supermarket, I promise my daughter Noor,
وفي السوق التجاري، أعد ابنتي نور بأنها إذا قالت لي "شكرًا"
I won't say, "Dis, 'Merci, Maman,'" and hope no one has heard her.
لن أقول لها "قولي شكرًا يا ابنتي" (بالفرنسية) وأنا أتمنى ألا يكون قد سمعها أحد!
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Let's get rid of this cultural cringe.
دعونا نتخلص من عقدة الأجنبي.